<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exhales</title>
    <description>Expressions of thoughys as breath.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 09:11:56 +1100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 09:11:56 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Empowering the Node &amp; Avoiding Enclosure</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This talk was given at the dLRN15 Conference on Saturday the 17th of October 2015 at Stanford University, Palo Alto. The talk is also available as a video (recorded after the live session) on &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/nu1cDxU3JRo&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I wanted to present on two things - one is an observation of a significant problem. The other is to put forward a proposal for a way forward in which to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to introduce this term of Enclosure to describe what I think has been happening on the web since the emergence of social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enclosure is a term from the Agricultural revolution and it&amp;#39;s used to descibe the process that ended the ancient system of farming in open fields. Rather than individual farmlands there was the commons and everyone had a right to farm in the commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enclosure was the process of putting up fences on the commons and moving ownership of  property from the community into private hands. This process generated massive social and economic change. To the power dynamics, social structures and the levels of individual and community autonomy. It created new classes of people and an economic and social structure that relied on exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways this is what I see happening in today’s digital networks? A case of history repeating itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original concept of the web was that we all would have our own websites. These would be our own place to create, store and publish. We would create a &amp;quot;commons&amp;quot; in which we share knowledge. And that through this digital network a social space would emerge out of this big open system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web was designed to be distributed. A network without a central point of failure or control. In this way nodes could connect in a multitude of different ways, networks would emerge in independant and evolving ways able to be reshaped to suit the needs of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today&amp;#39;s digital networks are built on systems that look like this. Centralised around a single database. A single point of failure. A single point of observation. A database able to be harnessed for commercial interests and effects. And while the number of nodes that these systems can support is amazing, they operate in isolation. A node in Facebook cannot connect to the one on Twitter. A node in the LMS cannot connect with LinkedIn. This is regardless of whether that node is the same person or not. By simply using these systems we are forced to create multiple identities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have moved to a model where we essentialy put our stuff into other peoples containers. We&amp;#39;ve given up it seems on the open  spaces. Where once we shared, the fences have now been put up. Fences that keep  the ability for us and our data to connect and be shared - separate and contained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We put our photos on flickr, our resume on LinkedIn, our personal lives on Facebook, our location on Foursquare. And from that point on the data doesn’t live in the commons. It doesn’t even live in our own domain it goes into these silos. We become renters of our own information. We become nodes not in a network of our own, but in someone elses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s not just in how we use these networks that encloses our data. These businesses also have a variety of practices that they often exploit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acquisition of data&lt;/strong&gt; – where the actual system of startups and venture capital actual promote a culture of build and sell out. The strategy becomes accumulation of users and associated data which becomes the assest used to leverage a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Binary choice&lt;/strong&gt; – signup to these networks is limited two options -  accept or decline. There is no way to negotiate terms, understand them or choose licensing options before you sign up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Licencing and ownership of digital objects&lt;/strong&gt; - when we sign up to the terms of service quite often what we are doing is granting that company a perpetual licence to use our data. It&amp;#39;s not granting them ownership - but in a digital rather than analogue world, what is the difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proprietary formats&lt;/strong&gt; - And finally, by creating proprietry formats our data often becomes locked in to their system. This means that there is little portability of our data - we can&amp;#39;t move it between networks, it becomes anchored to a single system which in many ways is defeats the purpose of being digital!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to think about this enclosure is outlined in the Hacker Manifesto that was written by McKenzie Wark back in 2004, important to note that this was before the rise of social media. In the book Wark suggested that what was occurring was the rise of a Vectoralist Class - the owners of the vectors - the various pathways and networks over which information flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nod to Marx, rather than owning the means of productions the Vectoralists own and exploit the means of transmission. They may own the wires and the cables, but increasingly they own the platforms through which we consume and share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vectoralists commidify information. They exploit information as a resource for capital. Our information, our data, becomes the commodity that they trade with. We are being exploited in order for them to make a profit. &amp;quot;Our&amp;quot; digital networks feed these commericial concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the best example of how the Vectoralist model isn&amp;#39;t a theory, it&amp;#39;s become reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uber, the world’s largest taxi company, owns no vehicles. Facebook, the world’s most popular media owner, creates no content... And Airbnb, the world’s largest accommodation provider, owns no real estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2015/03/03/in-the-age-of-disintermediation-the-battle-is-all-for-the-customer-interface/&quot;&gt;Tom Goodwin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power and money has shifted to those who can connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the valuation on these networks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook valuation $US250 billion July 2015
Uber valued at more than $US50 Billion July 2015
AirBnB valued at over $25 billion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our data and the networks that it travels through are incredibly vauable. In many ways too valuable. Too valuable to be comdified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too valuable to be trusted to these younger, hipper fat cats who are driven by a profit motive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_21.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we avoid enclosure &amp;amp; stop the rise of the vectoralists?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The Proposition - Empowering the Node&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_22.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common element in any network are the nodes. The individuals that make up the network, and it&amp;#39;s important to think of them as people - not as users. And people should have the right to be free and autonomous on the web just as they are in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is not the creation of new networks or alternative to Facebook or Twitter. As Mike suggested - getting away from the stream and think more about the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to move beyond the creation of networks as data containers which can be commodified and commercialised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_23.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead we need to focus on developing systems, tools and methods that empowered the node. Ways that allow each node to establish control over their digital lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide individuals the power to negotiate their networks and move seamlessly between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To smash the silos and the surveillance, to not just reclaim our domain but to extend it with the ability to generate new networks of our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a new model that supports a quite different approach to social, economic, political and technological issues in the digital space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_25.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whats interesting is that there are a range of emerging technologies and practices that provide a glimpse into how this could happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concepts like federation, APIs and the blockchain provide an insight into how all this could work. You may not understand what all of these things are - but understand that there are people in the tech world who are working at reshaping the available technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s something I am interested in pursuing because I think it&amp;#39;s an opportunity to reimagine networks - how they are created, how they are governed and for those of us at this conference - how they can be used to learn and grow and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_26.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that I&amp;#39;ve been fleshing out over the last 6 months or so is MYOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a multi-purpose accronym that is an attempt to encapsulate how this might work and how we could create it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_27.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mind your own stuff&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At it&amp;#39;s heart is the concept of a domain. Building on the work that Jim Groom and his team have been working towards we need to start with having a space, a store and a server to do this all on. But the focus of MYOS is to think beyond our own space, and to look at how we might connect woith others. How might we create our networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_28.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make your own space&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we could reimagine Facebook, Twitter and the LMS as spaces for networks rather than the containers of them? What would be possible then? What could we do if we could negotiate our own terms, to move beyond the binary of accept or decline. Part of myos would be that it would be quite simple and easy to create our own networks without the need for the massive overhead of server infrastructure and centralised management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My online self&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As people we are multifaceted. We have different aspects to our lives, we take on different personas, we socialise with different groups. We need technology that can support a better understanding of ourselves as complex human beings rather than data in a table. We need to be able manage our identity online, not have it defined by LinkedIn or Facebook. We shouldn&amp;#39;t have to manage complex privacy settings that are open to change at any moment. We shouldn&amp;#39;t have to fill in another online form so our personal information can yet again be held in  another database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_30.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My operating system&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what if we could make this as simple to run as your phone? By developing a backend structure that combined hardware and software you could add new features in much the same way you install an app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_31.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could add in a variety of features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A way to manage your identity, your memberships, your personal records, display your badges and qualifications, share your publications, create galleries of images, develop a portfolio of your work, or collect your notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea would be to create something adaptable to the individual, supportive of your own needs,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_32.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I call all of this is Nodeware - A combination of hardware and software that can change the underlying structure of systems from centralised to decentralised. From institutional to individual. From controlled to free. From closed to open. Something that allows us to create &lt;a href=&quot;http://hapgood.us/2015/10/17/the-garden-and-the-stream-a-technopastoral/&quot;&gt;Mike Caulfield&amp;#39;s Garden&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MYOS embodies the following priciples to Empower the Node:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_33.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) You are in control - that as a node you get to make the decisions, they&amp;#39;re not made for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_34.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Data is yours - your data is sovereign and it should be treated that way. You should have authority over how your data is shared and used. Who can access it and for how long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_35.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Connections are negotiated - rather than simply sign away to terms of service we need to ensure that democratic values are not lost. Networks require trust to work effectively so it&amp;#39;s importatnt that both sides are explicit about what and how they are willing to work. Systems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_36.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Enhance and enable diversity - Rather than enforce a monoculture, MYOS aims to promote diversity. We live in a complex world and we need to service that complexity rather than limit and While there is a need for a stable core, MYOS should promote a diverse eco-system of applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_37.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are gathered here today to discuss digital learning networks then we acknowledge that they are incredibly useful and meaningful. But we must also accept that the networks that we currently use are limited because of the underlying models and the technologies that support them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_38.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to change the model and change the mindset. To become distributed, to be more co-opertative, to promotoe more autonomy and ultimately be more connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_39.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To  not just create new vectors, but create a new commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/empowering-the-node/dLRN_Page_40.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank You!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 19:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>/presentation/2015/11/27/empowering-the-node-avoiding-enclosure.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/presentation/2015/11/27/empowering-the-node-avoiding-enclosure.html</guid>
        
        <category>myos</category>
        
        <category>enclosure</category>
        
        <category>reclaim</category>
        
        
        <category>presentation</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media: A story of Exploitation, Enclosure and Enslavement</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Social Media: A story of Exploitation, Enclosure and Enslavement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk was given at the Wagga Nerd Nite event on Tuesday the 24th of November 2015. To give it some context - it was originally planned to be given on September 24th but unfortunately that was the day of &lt;a href=&quot;https://timklapdor.wordpress.com/2015/09/25/the-fire/&quot;&gt;The Fire&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement/Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I wanted to present some of my observations about the emergent behaviours of social media companies and peel back the veneer of PR and advertising and take a look at what&amp;#39;s happening behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of quick questions: Who has a Facebook account?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who’s tagged someone else in a photo or post?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who’s changed their relationship status? What I&amp;#39;d like you to do is think about those answers and how they fit in the narrative we&amp;#39;re going to explore. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to start this story 25 years ago when this, the pager, was the height of technology – something really big began to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year the web is 25 years old, and while that might seem old, its important to understand how relatively young it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what the web looked like back in 1990. And we’ve come such a long way since, but it&amp;#39;s important to understand that the web is emergent - in the sense that no one really planned on it developing the way it has, nor was there ever a grand masterplan. This has meant that it&amp;#39;s incredibly adaptable to change and has allowed it to evolve along with the technology that powers it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to  preface this talk with a few things. I built my first web site 19 years ago while on work experience in Year 10, so I consider myself an early adopter. And since then I&amp;#39;ve myself a resident of the web, conducting my work, professional and social life through this medium. And as such I&amp;#39;m someone keenly interested in exploring it&amp;#39;s possibilities and pioneering its practices. So I believe in the web - this idea of a connected planet, through which we can all share freely and by doing so prosper. And I believe in this idea of a vast, open and distributed network that allows the world to share its knowledge and wealth of information beyond the concept of borders and nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_09.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Social Media is not the web. The reality is that the emergence of commercial enterprises operating online as &amp;quot;social media&amp;quot; has perverted that dream. And a lot it comes down to how these systems are built. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web was designed as a distributed system. Each node connects to each other which creates a resilient and robust system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast Social Media operates as seperate centralised systems. Connected but dependant on interfacing via this central component. While they sell themselves as enablers of connection you can see that you what you can connect with only occurs within one network. They&amp;#39;ve set themselves up as the middle-man. You also can’t branch out between Facebook into Twitter. This is not how the Web was designed to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what am I talking about when it comes to Social Media?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key identifier is this concept of “sharing&amp;quot;. This is technology for a group not the individual. It’s not like the apps on your computer or phone that are about personal productivity. They are about the socialised sharing of data, images and communications&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this broader definition includes - messaging applications (twitter, whats app, snapchat), image apps (flickr, instagram) but social media extends to things like LinkedIn and Foursquare and new players like Uber and Airbnb that depend on social and shared data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally there&amp;#39;s Facebook. Aaron Sorkin identified them as The Social Network, and they are the biggest and perhaps most influential company operating in this space so we&amp;#39;ll take a very specific look at what they&amp;#39;ve been up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to introduce this term of Enclosure to describe what I believe has been happening on the web since the emergence of social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enclosure is a term from the Agricultural revolution and is the term used to descibe the process that ended the ancient system of farming in open fields. It essentially ended the concept of the Commons - community land which was shared in order for everyone to benefit. Enclosure was when the fences were put up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Property moved from the commons into private hands - and this process generated massive social and economic change. It started the agricultural revolution and the industrial revolution but creating new classes of people, some who would become rich and powerful but most who would become exploited as slaves to the industrial machinations of the west.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does this apply to Social Media? To me it&amp;#39;s a case of history repeating itself. The original concept of the web was that we all would have our own websites. These would be our own place to create, store and publish. We would create a &amp;quot;commons&amp;quot; in which we share knowledge. And it happened because of the way the web was designed - to be distributed. These centralised platforms are the equivalent of throwing up fences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what we end up with is not this great network, but silos. Great big silos but none the less silos that are walled off, separated and controlled. The “network&amp;quot; isn’t open in the way it once was. What we&amp;#39;ve ended up with is a model where we put our stuff into other peoples containers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_21.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We put our photos on flickr, our resume on LinkedIn, our personal lives on Facebook, our location on Foursquare. And from that point on the data doesn’t live in the commons. A part from our direct contribution there are other techniques that are used to enclose our data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_22.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acquisition of data. Venture capital and the buy-out culture of startups has  meant that our data often becomes an asset, often the only asset, worth being acquired. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_23.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controlling the flow and shaping experience. A good example of this is how Facebook deals with video where it slows and reduces exposure if video comes from an external source like YouTube when compared to uploading it directly into Facebook. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Binary choice. This is a reference to the binary choice we are given when faced with the 50 or so pages of legalese in the Terms and Conditions. There&amp;#39;s no oportunity to negotiate, no way to limit or argue. You simply accept and can use the system or decline and be locked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_25.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Licencing and ownership of digital objects. While none of these sites are quite as bold as to claim ownership of your data, what you&amp;#39;ll often find hidden away in those terms and conditions is the fact that you&amp;#39;re granting these companies a perpetual license to use your data however they want. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_26.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we have to ask ourselves some really important questions. So who owns your data? Who and how do they define your identity? When you&amp;#39;re no longer in control of your data what&amp;#39;s really going on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_27.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite frankly it&amp;#39;s Exploitation. What’s happening is that once you’ve put your data in then these companies they use this to test and experiment on you. You become part of their universe and domain, a resource they can utilise in a purely cynical and exploitative manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_28.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the social graph and it&amp;#39;s Facebook&amp;#39;s attempt to map out all the data it has access to. To map out all the relationships between data and indiviuals, what we Like, who we like, who we are connected to. Every comment, picture, post and like is mined for relationships. And unknowingly or not we don&amp;#39;t just contributes the collection of data, we do their job for them by tagging our location which goes in along side the time stamp of when, who we were with and what we were doing. So what&amp;#39;s the value in that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means they can create a means of targeting individuals with a laser like focus… especially for advertising which is the main source of income currently.  Mainstream media – newspapers, radio, television - these are scatter gun approaches to engage with individuals, finding your target and appealing to them. This means that into the future advertising on social media will become far more valuable to advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_30.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s what’s led to the explosive valuations (July 2015) attached to these companies: Facebook valuation $US250 billion, Uber valued at more than $US50 Billion and AirBnB valued at over $25 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_31.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this value is reflected in the notion of Metcalfe’s Law where the value is all proportional to the number of users connected to the system. Basically the bigger you are the more valuable your are, and Facebook is worth the most because it is the biggest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_32.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It begs the question too - are we “sharing” or “giving”? Have they changed the notion of what sharing actually means? Or do we need to question this notion of what “sharing” actually means on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_33.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, before the rise of social media, McKenzie Wark published the Hacker Manifesto and suggested that what was occurring was the rise of a Vectoralist Class - the owners of the vectors - the various pathways and networks over which information flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_34.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than capitalists versus proletarians, the central antagonism was between hackers and vectoralists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_35.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of owning the means of productions they own and exploit the means of transmission - the vectors through which data travels. They own the wires and the cables, the platforms through which we consume and share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_36.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vectoralists commidify information. They exploit information as a resource for capital. Our information, our data, becomes the commodity that they trade with. We are being exploited in order for them to make a profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_37.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember those market evaluations? Well that’s despite the following: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Uber, the world’s largest taxi company, owns no vehicles. Facebook, the world’s most popular media owner, creates no contenthttp://exhal.es. And Airbnb, the world’s largest accommodation provider, owns no real estate.&amp;quot; 
-&lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2015/03/03/in-the-age-of-disintermediation-the-battle-is-all-for-the-customer-interface/&quot;&gt;Tom Goodwin&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They own virtually nothing that is physical or a tangible good, simply the vectors through which data travels&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_38.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the Vectoralist model in action. It&amp;#39;s not theory. It is our reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_39.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uber owns no infrastructure, no equipment. It simply owns the app the connects the driver to the passenger. This is perhaps the clearest example of owning vector between these two points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_40.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the same with AirBnB - they own the vector that joins the room with traveller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_41.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the new vectors through which money and power now travels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_42.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it brings us to Enslavement. If this can get darker, it does. What powers these sites and provide these companies with their power are the algorithms. They are ways of interrogating data in order to make a prediction. And what&amp;#39;s scary is that these algorithms are hidden from view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_43.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these algorithms then go onto to make predictions - if X knows Y then they should know Z and so heres a suggested friend. That’s nice huh? Or if X is 24, likes Y has more than 100 friends then target him with this ad. And thats great, another happy customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_44.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment these algorithms are designed for advertising because it’s paying the bills at Facebook. They&amp;#39;re pretty benign and can be quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_45.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if those same algorithms got into the hands of the secret police or the military in an oppresive government? What if they got hacked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_46.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So back at the beginning who changed their relationship status? Well that&amp;#39;s not all Facebook knows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_47.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Social Graph Facebook can cross reference that data with the huge array of information they&amp;#39;ve gathered on you. And those algorithms can mine that to determine your sexual orientation, political tendencies and probably a variety of indiscretions you don’t want anyone to know about. Because it knows when, where, and who you were with. And we told them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_48.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does your best fried know that information about you? When Facebook knows more about you than your best friend - you should be scared. The centralised and enclosed nature of these systems actually facilitate this surveillance to occur, by making it easy for this “big data” to accumulate. They have placed themselves in the middle of every single connection on their network - the ultimate and perfect panopticon.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_49.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algorithms are the dark side of social media because we can&amp;#39;t see how they manipulate what we see. It’s a known unknown – we know that the timeline changes and shifts around what we see and what we don&amp;#39;t - but we don’t know how, nor the motivations behind them. Is it because someone paid them to advertise or becasue a government made a request? These algorithms are the power behind Social Media and they are hidden from us. Jesus this is all pretty doom and gloom...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_50.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Wark mentions another class - the Hackers. His definition is a little more expansive than just notion computer hackers - they are sources of innovation, knowledge, and abstraction — the creators and makers. The people that don’t care about the commodity, they care about the act. They do this out of passion, out of a drive to do it differently, to conceive the new, the future. The Hacker Class generates alternatives to the current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_51.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vectoralists are the new fat cats. They may look young and hip and cool, but they are following the same model of exploitation and enslavement of the industrialists.  They make money by exploiting our of data and our effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_52.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So originally I was going to end here with a stirring call to action. Where we need to throw off the shackles of our oppressors and rebel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_53.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the banners unfurled and united we stand against the onslaught of social media facists who seek to enslave us. That united and together we can be free!) But.... I don&amp;#39;t feel quite so militant anymore. I think we need change, but for quite different reasons. You see the day of the last Nerd Nite, I was heading home early to practice this presentation when I got a phone call from the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_54.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I turned into my street to see 3 fire trucks and a cacophony of flashing lights. Someone had broken into our place and then set it on fire. They&amp;#39;d taken the stuff that was worth something to sell and then set fire to the rest of it. We lost photos and memorabilia, toys and our clothes. All of it gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_55.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happened next was amazing.  Through social media there was an outpouring of support that neither my wife, nor I, could have ever imagined. Those networks connected us to people more than willing to offer help and support. People gave without question, including those well beyond our own personal networks. And at that point I realised that the reason to rebel, the reason to rethink and reenginneer the ways these systems are structured, is because they&amp;#39;re too important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_56.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too important to have profit come between our connecrtions and relationships. Too important to sacrifice our identity and privacy in order for a company to sell us fucking ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_57.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead tonight I want to end by saying that the aim of social networks should be on the connections and relationships, not profit. That they should empower the individual to connect with people and ideas and share and give to one another, not for profit. That we need to rethink our relationship, not with each other, but with corporate entities that seek to exploit and enslave us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://exhal.es/assets/article_images/exploitation-enclosure-enslavement//Tim-Nerd-Nite-V2_Page_58.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2015 07:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>/presentation/2015/11/25/Exploitation-Enclosure-and-Enslavement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/presentation/2015/11/25/Exploitation-Enclosure-and-Enslavement.html</guid>
        
        <category>exploitation</category>
        
        <category>enclosure</category>
        
        <category>enslavement</category>
        
        <category>surveillance</category>
        
        <category>social media</category>
        
        
        <category>presentation</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
